Guide to the Peter Straub Papers MSS.185
Fales Library and Special Collections
Peter Straub Papers
1955-2021
1970-2004
Fales Library and Special Collections
Straub, Peter, 1943-2022
MSS.185
85.25 Linear Feet in 60 boxes with unknown profiles, 32 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript box, 1 tall manuscript box, 1 flat-file folder, 6 record cartons, 1 flat box, and 5 oversize flat boxes
2 audiocassettes
3 CDs
2 sound discs
7 sound tape reels
1 videocassette
28 3.5" floppy disks
1 CD-ROM
Peter Francis Straub was an award-winning horror writer. He was known for introducing elements of postmodern fiction into the horror genre. He was the author of 18 novels, including two co-written with Stephen King. The Peter Straub Papers primarily contain Peter Straub's manuscripts and typescripts as well as his correspondence. Other materials include: planners; catalogs, bulletins, and periodicals; typescripts by other writers; and a small amount of media (including shellac and glass LPs).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of Series XV. Access to Series XV is restricted until the materials are reviewed and processed by an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter Straub in 2006; addtional materials were donated in 2007, 2008, 2009, 2016, 2022, and 2023. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2006.185, 2016.030, 2016.031, 2022.027, and 2023.044.
Arrangement
Series are primarily arranged chronologically, except where to do so would destroy the original order of the material; where the original folders contained material from a range of years, those folders are ordered by their earliest date, so "1997-2000," for example, comes before "1998-1999." In the case of Straub's manuscripts and typescripts, material was grouped by work and arranged chronologically within each group. Typescripts by other writers are organized alphabetically by the authors' last names to facilitate retrieval (there was no discernible original order). When folders are undated, they are grouped alphabetically and filed at the end of their respective series. When a box contains more than one series, the folder range for each series is given. Series XV has not been arranged by an archivist; the materials appear in the order they were recieved and are closed to researchers until the materials are reviewed and formerly processed by an archivist. Series XVII has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
This collection is described primarily at the box level, and is arranged into 17 series:
Series
Series I: Work by Peter Straub
Series II: Editorial Work
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Administrative Files
Series V: Personal Files
Series VI: Publicity
Series VII: Works by Others
Series VIII: Periodicals and Clippings
Series IX: Programs
Series X: Publishers Catalogs
Series XI: Audio
Series XII: Video
Series XIII: Data Media
Series XIV: Objects
Series XV: 2016 Accretions (restricted)
Series XVI: 2022 Accretion
Series XVII: 2023 Accretion
Biographical Note
Peter Francis Straub (b. March 2, 1943, Milwaukee, Wisconsin; d. September 4, 2022) was an author noted for his novels and short stories in the horror genre for which he has won the Bram Stoker Award, the World Fantasy Award, and the International Horror Guild Award, among others. He received a B.A. in English from University of Wisconson-Madison in 1965 and an M.A. in English from Columbia University in 1967.
While working on a Ph.D., in Dublin, Ireland, Straub completed his first novel, Marriages, published in 1973. Having moved to London, Straub's work began to shift toward the horror genre, after his agent suggested he write a gothic novel. The novels Julia and If You Could See Me Now followed in 1975 and 1977. But it was the following novel, Ghost Story (1979), that jumpstarted his career as one of the foremost authors in the genre. In 1981, Ghost Story was adapted for a film starring Fred Astaire.
Straub's success in the horror genre led to the beginning of a collaborative relationship with Stephen King. Together, they wrote two novels, The Talisman and Black House.
Peter Straub and his wife, Susan Straub née Bitker, married in 1966. Susan is the creator and director of Read to Me, a program that promotes and supports young mothers reading to their babies. They have two children, Ben and Emma. Peter Straub died in Brooklyn, New York on September 4, 2022.
Novels
Marriages (1973)
Julia (1975)
If You Could See Me Now (1977)
Ghost Story (1979)
Shadowland (1980)
Floating Dragon (1983)
The Talisman (with Stephen King) (1984)
Wild Animals (collects the novels Julia, If You Could See Me Now, and Under Venus) (1984)
Under Venus (1985)
Koko (1989)
Mystery (1990)
The Throat (1993)
The Hellfire Club (1995)
Mr. X (1999)
Black House (with Stephen King) (2001)
Lost Boy, Lost Girl (2003)
In The Night Room (2004)
A Dark Matter (2010)
The Skylark (2010)
Poetry
My Life in Pictures (1971)
Ishmael (1972)
Open Air (1972)
Leeson Park and Belsize Square: Poems 1970-1975 (1983)
Novellas
The General's Wife (1982)
Mrs. God (1990)
Pork Pie Hat (2010)
Collections
Houses Without Doors (1990)
Magic Terror (2000)
A Little Blue Book of Rose Stories (2004)
5 Stories (2007)
Books and Periodicals Edited by Peter Straub
Peter Straub's Ghosts (1995)
Conjunctions 39: The New Wave Fabulists (2002)
H.P. Lovecraft: Tales (2005)
American Fantastic Tales: Terror and the Uncanny from Poe to the Pulps (2009)
American Fantastic Tales: Terror and the Uncanny from the 1940s until now (2009)
Awards
2007 Bram Stoker Award: Superior Achievement in a collection, for 5 Stories
2003 Bram Stoker Award: Best Novel, for Lost Boy, Lost Girl
2003 International Horror Guild Award: Best Novel, for Lost Boy, Lost Girl
2000 Bram Stoker Award: Fiction Collection, for The Hellfire Club
1999 Bram Stoker Award: Best Novel, for Mr. X
1998 International Horror Guild Award: Best Long Form, for "Mr. Clubb and Mr. Cuff"
1998 Bram Stoker Award: Long Fiction, for "Mr. Clubb and Mr. Cuff"
1994 British Fantasy Award: Best Novel, for Floating Dragon
1993 World Fantasy Award: Best Novella, for "The Ghost Village"
1993 Bram Stoker Award: Best Novel, for The Throat
1989 World Fantasy Award: Best Novel, for Koko
Sources:
"About the Author." From http://www.peterstraub.net/bio/bio_home.html.
"Awards and Honors." From http://www.peterstraub.net/awards/awards_home.html.
"A Must Read: Peter '65 and Susan '66 Straub." From http://www.uwalumni.com/daa2009straub.aspx.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Peter Straub Papers document Peter Straub's long career as a horror novelist and highlight his relationship with friend and colleague, Stephen King. This collection primarily contains manuscripts and typescripts of Straub's published works, fragments of unpublished works, essays, lectures, and introductions for other authors' works; hand written, typed, and e-mail correspondence including letters from Stephen and Tabitha King; periodicals that include articles about Straub and essays and short stories that he published; and contractual documentation for donations to New York University's Fales Library and Special Collections and for Straub's 2006 appearance on his favorite daytime television series, "One Life to Live." Personal materials include Struab's diaries, notebooks, school records, and day planners. The collection also includes clippings about Straub and reviews of his work; programs for conventions and conferences that he attended, where he was often a speaker or feature author; adaptations of Straub's work for television, audio, and film; and numerous annotated manuscripts by authors who asked Straub to review their work, including Stephen King and Neil Gaimen. Works by Stephen King of Note are "The Dark Tower Series," "Misery," and "Tommyknockers." Materials also include computer programs on 3.5 inch floppy disks that Straub used including Norton Rescue Disc, AST Research, Inc., The Norton Desktop for Windows, Dos 6-22, Windows for Workgroups 3.11, Microsoft Intellipoint Professional, and a Kodak Picture CD. There are various audio recordings of speeches given by political figures such as Winston Churchill and programs featuring interviews with Straub, that were recorded on reel to reel magnetic tape, audiocassettes, compact discs, and photographic records. There is one videocassette featuring the show, "Prisoners of Gravity," a Canadian news program from the early 1990's that explored themes in speculative fiction.
Separated Materials
The following materials have been removed to the Fales American Collection:
Easton, M. & Shy, C. Soul stealer: book 1, hell among the rogues. Juno, A. & Vale, V. (Eds.). (1993). Bob Flanagan: super-masochist. San Francisco, CA: Re/Search Publications.
Authors, American -- 20th century.; Magnetic tapes.; Horror tales.; Compact discs.; Videocassettes.; VHS; Phonograph records.; Promotional materials; Manuscripts for publication.; Audiocassettes.; Manuscripts; Typescripts; Page proofs.; Correspondence.; Catalogs.; Morrow, Bradford, 1951-; Lethem, Jonathan; King, Stephen, 1947-; Lauterbach, Ann, 1942-; Oates, Joyce Carol, 1938-; Gaiman, Neil; Plante, David; Williams, Jonathan; Brite, Poppy Z.; Pelecanos, George P.; Harington, Donald; McGrath, Patrick, 1950-
- Series I: Work by Peter Straub, 1968-2007
  Arrangement
  Items in Subseries A are grouped by work, which are arranged chronologically by publication date. Items in Subseries D are arranged chronologically by pseudonym, with undated material arranged alphabetically by title under each pseudonym. All other subseries are arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Content
  Series I contains manuscripts, typescripts, and proofs of works by Peter Straub.
  - Subseries A: MSS and TSS of Published Books, 1970-2004
    Manuscripts and Typescripts are grouped by work, which are arranged chronologically by publication date.
    Subseries A contains manuscripts and typescripts of Peter Straub's published novels. Correspondence accompanying particular manuscripts and typescripts were not removed but were kept in their original locations.
    - Julia; If You Could See Me Now, 07/1970-02/1976 (Box 1)
    - If You Could See Me Now; Ghost Story, 06/1976-02/1978; undated (Box 2)
    - Ghost Story; Shadowland, 07/1978-07/1980 (Box 3)
    - Shadowland; Floating Dragon, 07/1979-07/1980 (Box 4)
    - Floating Dragon, 02/1982; undated (Box 5)
    - Floating Dragon; Talisman; Wild Animals, undated (Box 6)
    - Wild Animals; Under Venus, 1969; 1972; 1981; undated (Box 7)
    - Under Venus, 07/1982; 10/1981; 2000; undated (Box 8)
    - Koko, 06/1986-07/1987; undated (Box 9)
    - Koko, 02/1988-04/1988; undated (Box 10)
    - Koko, undated (Box 11)
    - Koko; Houses without Doors, 03/1988-07/1989; undated (Box 12)
    - Houses without Doors, 1987-1990; undated (Box 13)
    - Houses without Doors; Mystery, 09/1988-10/1988; undated (Box 14)
    - Mystery, undated (Box 15)
    - Mystery; The Throat, 09/1989-05/1992; undated (Box 16)
    - The Throat, 03/1992; 06/1992 (Box 17)
    - The Throat, 07/1992; undated (Box 18)
    - The Throat, undated (Box 19)
    - The Throat; Hellfire Club, 09/1993; 04/1994; 09/1994 (Box 20)
    - Hellfire Club, 09/1994; 03/1995 (Box 21)
    - Hellfire Club, 04/1995; undated (Box 22)
    - Hellfire Club, undated (Box 23)
    - Mr. X, 04/1996-03/1998 (Box 24)
    - Mr. X, 03/1998-06/1998 (Box 25)
    - Mr. X, 06/1998-09/1998 (Box 26)
    - Mr. X, 01/1999-12/1999 (Box 27)
    - Mr. X, undated (Box 28)
    - Mr. X, undated (Box 29)
    - Magic Terror, 01/1993-10/1998; undated (Box 30)
    - Magic Terror; Black House; Lost Boy, Lost Girl, 1999-2003 (Box 31)
    - Lost Boy, Lost Girl, 03/2003-05-2003 (Box 32)
    - In the Night Room, 09/2003-07/2004 (Box 33)
  - Subseries B: Poetry, Short Fiction, Fragments of Unpublished Work, 1968-2005
    Items in this subseries are arranged chronologically.
    Subseries B contains short creative works by Peter Straub, as well as short fragments of unpublished work.
    - Poetry and Short Fiction, 1968-01/2001 (Box 34)
    - Poetry and Short Fiction, 01/2001-05/2005; undated (Box 35)
      General
      Box includes some correspondence between Peter Straub and Michael Chabon.
  - Subseries C: Essays, Introductions, Lectures, 1998-2007
    Subseries C contains manuscripts and typescripts of essays, reviews, introductions and forewords, talks and lectures, and liner notes written by Peter Straub.
    - Essays, Introductions, Lectures, 1998-1998 (Box 35)
    - Essays, Introductions, Lectures, 03/1999-02/2007; undated (Box 36)
      Folders 1-45. (Folder 17 contains a typescript of the story "Lapland, or Film Noir.")
  - Subseries D: Pseudonymous Work, 11/1996-08/1998
    Subseries D is arranged chronologically by pseudonym, with undated material arranged alphabetically by title under each pseudonym.
    Subseries D contians work written by Straub under pseudonyms.
    Putney Tyson Ridge is the name of the (fictional) chairman Department of Popular Culture at Popham College (also fictional) in Popham, Ohio, through which Peter Straub wrote criticisms of his own books.
    Fionnuala Curry is a psuedonym Peter Straub briefly adopted in London in the early 1970s for the purpose of selling romantic stories to women's magazines.
    Kimberly Buggins is a fictional character Peter Straub invented for the amusement of David J. Schow. Schow and Straub are friends of the film director Frank Darabont, to whom Buggins's letters are addressed.
    - Putney Tyson Ridge, 11/1996-08/1998 (Box 36)
      Folders 46-67.
    - Fionnuala Curry, 02/08/1974; undated (Box 36)
      Folders 68-71.
    - Kimberly Buggins, 06/20/1998; undated (Box 36)
      Folder 72.
  - Subseries E: Galleys and Proofs, 1975-2004
    Subseries E contains galleys and proofs of various works by Peter Straub with comments, corrections, and annotations by Straub, editors, copy editors, and others.
    - Galleys and Proofs, 1975-1984 (Box 37)
    - Galleys and Proofs, 08/1995-2004 (Box 38)
    - Galleys and Proofs, 03/2004; undated (Box 39)
  - Subseries F: Miscellaneous Notebooks, 1967-1978, 1995, undated; Items in this subseries are arranged chronologically.
    Subseries F contains manuscript notebooks not associated with any single project.
    - Miscellaneous Notebooks, 1967-1978, 1995, undated (Box 40)
      Folders 1-16.
  - Subseries G: Periodicals, 1964-2009
    Subseries G contains clippings and periodicals that printed Peter Straub's fiction and nonfiction.
    - Periodicals with Peter Straub work, 1964-1994 (Box 40)
      Folders 17-29.
    - Periodicals with Peter Straub work, 11/1994-2009 (Box 41)
- Series II: Editorial Work, 1993-2005
  Series II is arranged chronologically by project: 1) HWA Presents Peter Straub's Ghosts, 2) Conjunctions 39, 3) H.P. Lovecraft: Tales, and 4) Seafront Press.
  Series II contains material (including typescripts and correspondence) related to Peter Straub's role as editor for various publications.
  - Editorial Work, 09/1993-10/1993; 06/2002-09/2002; 04/2003-04/2005; undated (Box 42)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1965-2008
  Series III is arranged chronologically, except where to do so would destroy the original arrangement of the correspondence (which is sometimes grouped by addressee or subject); where this is so, the folders of such a group are arranged chronologically and are filed with the rest of the correspondence chronologically according the the earliest date of the group. All undated material is filed at the end of the series.
  Series III contains postal and email correspondence to and from Peter Straub, with some correspondence addressed to Susan Straub (née Bitker).
  - Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box 43)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1992 (Box 44)
    Box includes correspondence from Stephen King, Ann Lauterbach, Jonathan Williams, Patrick McGrath.
  - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 45)
    Box includes correspondence from Jonathan Williams.
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 46)
    Box includes correspondence from Ann Lauterbach, Stephen King, Donald Harington, Neil Gaiman
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 47)
    Box includes correspondence from Stephen King, Joyce Carol Oates.
  - Correspondence, 1998-2002 (Box 48)
    Box includes correspondence from George Pelecanos, Stephen King.
  - Correspondence, 2002-2008; undated (Box 49)
    Box includes correspondence from Poppy Z. Brite, Chester Brown, Michael Dirda, John Crowley, Jonathan Letham, David Sim, Ann Lauterbach, A.M. Holmes.
- Series IV: Administrative Files, 1972-2008
  Series IV contains financial records, charitable contributions, contracts and agreements, royalty statements, board minutes (Fence magazine), material (including correspondence) relating to a Columbia University writing class taught by Straub, and material regarding Straub's appearance on One Life to Live.
  - Administrative Files, 1972-2008 (Box 50)
    No Subnote Content
- Series V: Personal Files, 1984-2008
  Series V is arranged chronologically.
  Series V contains Peter Straub's planners, diaries, graduate school material, personal photographs, awards and certificates, and other material not related specifically to his professional roles.
  - Subseries A: Planners and Diaries, 01/1984-2006
    Subseries A contains Peter Straub's planners and diaries.
    - Planners, 01/1984 - 2006 (Box 51)
  - Subseries B: Graduate School, x
    Items in this subseries are arranged chronologically. Undated material is arranged alphabetically at the end of the file.
    Subseries B contains notes, thesis drafts, and other material related to Peter Straub's M.A. at Columbia University.
    - Graduate School, 1965-1966 (Box 51)
      Folders 17-19.
    - Graduate School, 1966; undated (Box 52)
      Folders 1-4.
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous Personal, 1965-2008; undated
    Subseries VI contains various personal documents of Peter Straub's.
    - Miscellaneous Personal, 1800s; 1965; 08/1982; 2008; undated (Box 52)
      Folders 5-43.
- Series VI: Reviews and Publicity, 1975-2005; undated
  Series VI is arranged chronologically.
  Series VI contains computer print-out, photocopies, and periodicals of published reviews of Straub work and interviews with Straub; author photographs; promotional photographs; book cover samples; and other promotional material.
  - Reviews and Publicity, 1975-1988 (Box 52)
    Folders 44-55.
  - Reviews and Publicity, 1989-2001 (Box 53)
  - Reviews and Publicity, 1999-2008 (Box 54)
  - Reviews and Publicity, 1999-2007; undated (Box 55)
- Series VII: Works by Others, 1984-2006
  Subseries A is arranged alphabetically by author's last name. When the author is unknown, items appear at the end of the subseries and are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Subseries B is arranged chronologically.
  Series VII contains unpublished work by other writers, mostly typescripts, as well as adaptations and treatments of Peter Straub works for television, film, and audio. The series is divided into two subseries: one comprising work composed by other writers; the other, adaptations and treatments of Peter Straub works.
  - Subseries A: Works by Others, 1984-2006
    Items in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by author's last name. When the author is unknown, items appear at the end of the subseries and are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    Subseries A contains manuscripts, typescripts, proofs, and photocopies of works by other authors, including Stephen King. One broadside, a poem by Charles Bernstein, is included in this subseries.
    - Work by Others (Bernstein-Clute), 1997; 2006; undated (Box 55)
      Box includes typescript by Poppy Z. Brite, Are You Loathsome Tonight.
    - Work by Others (Bruhm-Joyce), 1984-2006; undated (Box 56)
      Box includes typescript by John Crowley, Egypt.
    - Work by Others (Kiernan-King), undated (Box 57)
      Box includes typescripts by Stephen King, "The Boys of Summer," The Dark Tower Vol. 7, and Needful Things
    - Work by Others (King-Winter), 1988; 2003; 2006; undated (Box 58)
      Folders 1-13.
      Box includes typescripts by Stephen King, Pet Cemetery and "Rainy Season;" Bradford Morrow, Giovanni's Box; David Plante, The Age of Terror and The Ghost in the Forest; David Schow, Bullets of Rain.
    - Dedication by Stephen King, undated (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Misery by Stephen King, undated (Box 75, Folder 2-3)
    - The Mustache by Emmanuel Carrer, 1986 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - The Tommyknockers by Stephen King, undated (Box 75, Folder 5-6, Box 76, Folder 1-2)
    - Photocopied short stories, undated (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - Never Visit Venice by Robert Aickman, undated (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Photocopied short stories, undated (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Tales by Moonlight II For Books, unknown (Box 76, Folder 6, Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Subseries B: Adaptations of Peter Straub Work, 1988-2003
    Subseries B contains adaptations of Straub's work for television, audio, and film.
    - Adaptations of Peter Straub Work, 1988-1989; 1991 (Box 58)
      Folders 14-22.
    - Adaptations of Peter Straub Work, undated (Box 59)
- Series VIII: Periodicals and Clippings, 1983-2006; undated
  Series VIII is arranged chronologically.
  Series VIII contains periodicals and other ephemeral publications collected in the Peter Straub Papers that do not directly mention Peter Straub or his works. Some correspondence is included.
  - Periodicals and Clippings, 1983-2006; undated (Box 60)
    Folders 1-12.
- Series IX: Programs, 1984-2008; undated
  Series IX is arranged chronologically.
  Series IX contains programs from writer's conferences.
  - Programs, 1984-2008; undated (Box 60)
    Folders 13-24.
- Series X: Publisher Catalogs, 11/1989; 07/1999-01/2000; 2003; 06/2008
  Series X is arranged chronologically.
  Series X contains catalogs from publishing houses.
  - Publisher Catalogs, 11/1989; 07/1999-01/2000; 2003; 06/2008 (Box 60)
    Folders 25-27.
- Series XI: Audio, 1994; 2000; 2004; undated
  Items in this series are arranged chronologically. Most items are given an ID number. When that number is followed by an "A," it indicates that the item was separated from paper material in which it was originally housed (e.g., record sleeve) or that was originally housed along with the item (e.g., scrap of paper in CD jewel case). Those paper materials have been moved to a separate subseries and given a matching number followed by a "B." In the case of items 185.0007A-185.0009A and items 185.0010A-185.0012A, each set of discs was originally stored in a large envelope, which now bears the series of ID numbers for those discs.
  Scope and Contents